大家好 我是Animagraffs的制作人Jake O'Neal
I'm Jake O'Neal, creator of Animagraffs.
这是洛克希德生产的SR-71黑鸟式侦察机
And this is the Lockheed SR-71 Blackbird.
SR-71自1966年起服役美国空军
The SR-71 entered service in the United States Air Force in 1966
定位为侦察机 也就是间谍飞机
as a reconnaissance aircraft, or in other words, a spy plane.
机上无炸弹或机枪
It doesn't carry bombs or have onboard guns.
它的御敌法宝是其无可匹敌的飞行速度与高度
Its main defense against enemy action is altitude and speed which made it essentially invulnerable,
巡航速度3.2马赫 即3.2倍声速 约2200英里/小时
sustaining Mach 3.2, that is 3.2 times the speed of sound, which roughly correlates to about 2,200+ miles per hour,
巡航高度高达85000英尺
at altitudes up to 85,000 feet.
SR-71从未被击落过
No SR-71 was ever shot down.
哪怕导弹或敌机飞到了SR-71的高度 飞行员一脚油门就能甩开它们
To evade missiles or hostile aircraft, if they could even reach the SR-71's altitude, pilots simply outran them.
这款杰作的每一部分都是为其任务目标而设计的
Every part of this masterpiece is designed for its mission goals.
我们先大致看下飞机外观 了解这些任务目标是如何转化为实物设计的
Let's have a general look around the plane
to get an idea of how those goals translate into the physical design of things,
之后再深入了解每个系统的细节
before we zoom in on the finer details of each system.
与当时其他战斗机或侦察机相比 黑鸟是一款相对较大的飞机
The Blackbird is a relatively large airplane compared to other fighter or reconnaissance craft of the era.
以难以企及的高度和速度飞行需要大量燃油
Flying at untouchable altitudes and speeds simply requires a lot of fuel.
机身三分之二的体积 与机翼内的可用空间都被油箱占据
Two-thirds of the fuselage are occupied by cylindrical fuel tanks, and any usable space in the wings,
总容量为12219.2加仑
for a total capacity of 12,219.2 gallons (46,254.7 L),
燃油重量约80285磅
weighing in at around 80,285 pounds (36416.7 kg) of fuel.
两台动力强劲的喷气发动机固定在机翼两侧
A pair of powerful jet engines are secured into the wings at both sides.
发动机的外圈主要部分称为"短舱"
A substantial portion of this compartment, called the nacelle,
用于安装大型可移动进气锥
is dedicated to large movable inlet cones called "spikes"
我们稍后会介绍 进气锥对SR-71的超音速能力至关重要
which, as we'll see later, are critical for the SR-71's supersonic speed capabilities.
机翼后部有一排襟翼 称为升降副翼
A row of flaps along the back of the wing, called elevons,
外加每个短舱顶部的方向舵 构成了飞机的飞行控制面
and rudders perched atop each nacelle, make up the flight control surfaces for the plane.
飞机前部有两个座舱
Heading to the front, there are two cockpits,
前面是飞行员
for the pilot,
后面是侦察系统官
and Reconnaissance Systems Officer respectively.
驾驶舱周围是设备舱 可根据任务需要安装各种组件
Equipment bays surround the cockpits and can be fitted with an array of components depending on the mission,
还有个可拆卸的机头部分
as well as the removable nose section.
现在让我们来了解一下细节 先从外部空气动力学入手
Now let's get into the details, starting with the exterior aerodynamics.
在地面上 发动机呈略向下倾斜状态
The engines appear to be tilted slightly downwards on the ground.
在巡航高度和速度下 它们更接近于水平
At cruising altitude and speed they're closer to level,
此时机身机翼达到设计的6度抬头 即"攻角"
with the fuselage and wing designed to sit at 6 degrees positive rotation or "angle of attack".
为携带足够燃油 设备和人员 飞机的机身和机头相当长
To carry sufficient fuel, equipment, and personnel, the fuselage and nose of the plane is quite long.
黑鸟采用三角翼布局 英文"delta"来自希腊字母"Δ"
The Blackbird has a delta wing design, so called for its triangular shape like a greek "Δ" character.
正如SR-71的设计目的一样 超过声速 或者说"超音速"
Exceeding the speed of sound, or "going supersonic", as the SR-71 was designed to do
意味着要对空气分子施加强大的力
means pushing hard against air molecules.
空气分子是真实存在的物质 像弹性网状结构一样交织在一起
Air molecules are real physical things, bonded together in a sort of elastic mesh,
当这些分子相互撞击时 就会发出声音
and sound happens when those molecules ram into each other,
最终使你的耳鼓发生振动
to eventually physically jiggle your ear drum.
这些分子之间的间距 它们各自的重量 它们之间作用力的强度等等
The spacing of these molecules, their individual weight, the strength of the elastic bonds between them, and so on,
都让这张空气网具有可预测的行为
gives this air mesh predictable behavior.
如果你撞击这些分子的速度超过了它们相互撞击的速度
If you slam through these molecules faster than they can crash into themselves,
那么你就超过了声速
you're exceeding the speed of sound.
在地面相对正常的条件下 这个速度是760英里/小时
On the ground, this happens at around 760 mph in relatively normal conditions.
由于空气分子无法以足够快的速度避开
Since they can't move out of the way fast enough,
它们在撞击到飞机突出的部分时会聚集在一起
air molecules bunch up when they hit parts of the plane that stick out,
形成具有可预测特性的激波
forming shock waves that have predictable characteristics.
比如角度会随着速度的增加而变大
Like angles that get sharper with increasing speed.
准确地讲 在3.2马赫巡航时 激波角为18度
18 degrees, to be precise, at Mach 3.2 cruising speed.
我们将传统飞机的机翼放入画面中
Let's throw a more standard wing into the mix.
由于它们的后掠角更小
Because these wings have much less sweepback angle,
机翼要直面机头产生的激波 大大增加阻力
the nose shock wave blasts into them, causing a brick wall of drag to slow the plane down.
如果把后掠翼收进机头激波范围内
If you try to sweep them back far enough to tuck into the nose shock wave,
机翼与机身的连接部分又会变得脆弱
the attachment point at the fuselage gets flimsy.
观察三角翼是如何解决这个问题的
Notice how the delta wing solves these issues.
经典空气动力学下的机翼外形非常适合在低速飞行时产生升力
The classic aerodynamic wing profile shape is excellent for generating lift at slower speeds.
但当我们接近超音速时
But as we approach supersonic speed,
机翼又厚又钝的前缘会导致空气在机翼前聚集 形成大量乱流
its thickness and blunt leading edge cause air to bunch up in front of the wing in a turbulent traffic jam.
这就是所谓的"音障"
Contributing to what's called the "sound barrier".
相反 对于SR-71来说 当压力随速度的增加而增大时
In contrast, as pressure builds with increasing speed,
其薄而锋利的三角翼会刺穿空气
the SR-71's sharp, thin wing slices through the air.
狭窄的机翼前缘使正在形成的激波最终附着在机翼前部
The narrow leading edge allows the developing shock wave to eventually attach itself to the front of the wing.
在超过声速时
At the speed of sound and above,
机翼尖锐的形状会将空气梳理成流动顺畅稳定的超音速激波
the plane's sharp features comb air into smooth flowing, well behaved supersonic shock waves
流过前缘和后缘
at leading and trailing edges.
两台发动机进气口与机身保持距离 防止卷起机身下方气流
The twin jet engines and their inlets are spaced out from the center to avoid air that swirls up from under the fuselage,
同时又能在最高速度下保持在机头激波中
but are still kept within the nose shock wave even at maximum speeds.
继续观察机身外部 注意到机身两侧各有一条标志性的脊线
As we continue observing the exterior, we see the characteristic ridges at each side of the fuselage.
chined forebody
在空气动力学中 机身两侧锋利的边缘称为"脊形(前体)"
In aerodynamic parlance, a sharp edge like this is called a chine.
脊形前体有几个重要作用
These chines serve a few critical tasks.
在飞行时 它们能在空气中带起更强大的涡流
They help form more powerful vortices as air swirls up around them during flight,
从而降低又薄又锋利的机翼上方的压力
which causes lower pressure above the sharp thin wings,
高速飞行时 它们的升力占总升力的20%
contributing an impressive 20% of total lift at speed.
在黑鸟飞行时 它们像鳍一样可以保持黑鸟修长的前机身稳定
They act like fins to stabilize the Blackbird's long nose as it cuts through the air.
雷达散射截面 Radar cross-section: https://zh.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E9%9B%B7%E8%BE%BE%E6%95%A3%E5%B0%84%E6%88%AA%E9%9D%A2
脊形前体还可以大大减少雷达散射截面
These chines also greatly reduce the radar cross-section.
雷达从一点向外发射电磁波
Radar towers beam signals from a point outwards.
常见的圆柱机身总会将其中一些电磁波反射回去
Common rounded plane features will reliably reflect some of those waves back
目标更容易从各种角度被识别
for easier identification from many angles.
黑鸟更平坦的表面降低了电磁波反射回来源的可能性
The Blackbird's flatter surfaces reduce the likelihood of waves reflecting back to the source.
出于同样原因 黑鸟的方向舵也是向内倾斜的
The rudders are also tilted or canted inwards for the same reason.
整机的雷达散射截面比它看起来得要小很多
Its radar cross-section makes it look much smaller than it is.
SR-71是首批有意采用这种隐形技术的作战飞机
The SR-71 was among the first operational aircraft with this kind of intentional stealth shaping.
黑鸟还采用了一种早期的雷达吸波复合材料 称为"塑料"
The Blackbird also featured an early radar-absorbing composite material, called plastic
虽然不是我们想象中的塑料
though not what we think of as plastic.
楔形的复合材料与钛金属沿外缘交错排布 便于高温下的膨胀
Composite wedges alternate with titanium along the outer rim in a zig-zag pattern to allow for expansion.
"塑料"在进气锥和方向舵上也有覆盖
This so-called plastic also covers inlet cones and rudders.
内部结构称为"机体" 主要由钛制成
The interior frame, called the airframe, is mostly made of titanium,
大部分外部镶板也由钛制成 确保其在极端压力和高温下的性能
as well as much of the exterior paneling, for its performance under extreme stress and heat.
在高速飞行时 有些表面可达700多华氏度 整个飞机会膨胀几英寸
Some surfaces could reach 700+ degrees, and the entire plane expanded several inches when traveling at speed.
机翼表面的波纹能在增强强度的同时实现尺寸的膨胀
Corrugations along the wing surface also allow expansion while contributing strength.
我们已经了解飞机外壳与内部机体是如何为飞机的超音速飞行服务的
Now that we've seen how the exterior shell and underlying airframe are made for supersonic flight,
接下来我们来说发动机
let's see how the engines get us there.
我们放大一侧的发动机
We'll zoom in on just one side.
15:50 介绍进气锥
前面是进气锥 我们稍后介绍
There's the inlet spike at the front, which we'll get to in a bit.
喷气发动机的本体位于后部 总体设计其实非常标准
The actual jet engine sits behind that, and has a pretty standard overall design.
空气进入喷气发动机后 被称为"转子"叶片环吹向后方
Air enters the jet engine and is forced backwards by rotating discs with blades, called rotors.
静止的叶片环称为定子
Rings of stationary blades called stators
可以确保空气总体向后流动并产生压力 而是与转子瞎搅和
make sure the air flows generally backwards and builds pressure, instead of just twisting with rotors.
气流通道变窄 压缩气体 让燃烧更充分
The passage narrows, compressing the air for more powerful combustion.
压缩后的空气流入几个不同的喷嘴
The compressed air now flows through separate nozzles,
空气从小喷嘴的外圈喷入
around a small outer ring
燃油从喷嘴中央喷入
while fuel is sprayed through the center.
随后油气混合物被点燃
The fuel-air mixture is ignited.
许多喷气发动机都使用点火器 与汽车的火花塞差不多
In many jet engines, ignitor plugs, not unlike a car spark plug, are used.
但SR-71不同 因为它使用的特殊燃油有自己的点火要求
But the SR-71 is different because of its special fuel that has its own ignition requirements.
24:55 介绍燃油
我们稍后会介绍
We'll look at that a little later.
点火后 火焰通过小型"交叉"管 直到所有燃烧罐体都被点燃
Once ignited, flame passes through small "cross-over" tubes until all burner cans are lit.
燃烧罐体中排出高速废气推动涡轮
The powerful exhaust shooting out of these cans pushes against turbines,
提供大约6万马力的动力
delivering something like 60,000 horsepower.
涡轮与内部的齿轮和轴相连接
Turbines are connected to internal gears and shafts
驱动压缩机转子吸入更多空气 继续燃烧循环
to drive those forward compressor rotors, sucking in more air and continuing the cycle.
排出的高温废气膨胀 形成高速射流 推动飞机前进
The exiting hot exhaust gas expands, creating a fast moving jet of air to push the plane forwards.
压缩机 燃烧室和涡轮 共同构成一台基本的涡轮喷气式发动机
This setup, with compressor, combustor, and turbine sections,
is the basic turbojet engine design.
如果想了解它在大型客机或现代战机上的工作原理
Animagraffs has a video about jet engines if you want to see how this looks in a big airliner, or a more modern fighter jet.
可以查看Animagraffs频道的往期视频
高性能发动机通常会有加力燃烧室 黑鸟亦然
High performance engines often have an afterburner section, and the Blackbird does as well.
经过燃烧后的高速废气中仍有可燃烧的空气
Fuel has been consumed, but there's still burnable air in the exiting exhaust stream.
因此 额外的燃油喷入高速废气中
Additional fuel is sprayed into this stream.
混合物流经被称为"火焰稳定器"的V形环上
The mixture wraps around V-shaped rings called flameholders,
它为燃油混合和燃烧提供了一个封闭的湍流区域
which provide a contained area of turbulence for fuel mixing and combustion.
混合物被点燃
This mixture is ignited.
多数应用情况中 加力燃烧室燃油效率低 但推力非常大
For most applications, afterburner is fuel inefficient but very powerful.
因此 通常用于瞬时加速
As such, it's limited to short bursts.
相反 黑鸟设计是在巡航速度下保持持续 完全的加力燃烧
In contrast, the Blackbird is designed to maintain continuous, full afterburner at cruising speed,
在每次空中加油间隔中持续一个小时左右
for an hour or so at a time between aerial refuelings.
现在 先前积累的热量与压力必须转换成废气的速度
All this heat and built up pressure must now be converted into exhaust velocity.
这个特殊的部分称为"渐缩渐阔喷管"/"拉伐尔喷管"
There's a special section here called a convergent-divergent nozzle.
高温高压的废气流在收窄段加速 通过喉部
Hot, pressurized jet exhaust speeds up to squeeze through the narrow part,
随后在出口的扩张段膨胀
and then expands through the wide exit,
将热量与压力转换成速度
converting all that heat and pressure into velocity.
一圈翼片组成"喷口"
There's a ring of flaps called the "ejector"
原文注: 可移动的喷口翼片
可以根据喷口内外的压力差进行调节
There are free-floating ejector flaps that adjust based on the pressure difference inside vs. outside the exhaust duct.
翼片可以改变喷口的大小 以便在不同条件下让废气得到适当的加速
that can alter the size of the exhaust opening for proper exhaust acceleration in varying conditions.
给废气加速就像用拇指捏住花园里的喷水管一样
Accelerating exhaust is something like sticking your thumb over a garden hose.
管道内的水流速慢 对管壁压强大
Water still in the hose moves slowly and pushes harder against hose walls.
水管捏得越用力 喷出来的水流就越强
The more you block the stream for a stronger spray at the end.
实际数值上讲 如果离开涡轮的气流速度是0.4马赫
In hard numbers, if air exiting the turbines is at Mach 0.4,
离开喷口的气流可以超过3马赫 以匹配飞机的巡航速度
air at the ejector flaps has accelerated to Mach 3 or more, to match the plane's traveling speed.
在20世纪50年代末 这种喷气机技术非常了不起
This late 1950's fighter jet technology is awesome,
但光靠它并不能维持3.2马赫的速度
but it's not capable of sustaining Mach 3.2 on its own.
事实上 喷气发动机甚至不能直接使用超音速气流
In fact, the jet engine can't even use supersonic air
因为这会导致发动机熄火 燃烧器停止工作等情况
as it would cause flameouts, extinguishing the combustor, among other things.
这就是进气锥发挥作用的地方
This is where the inlet spike comes into play.
在进气锥的尖端会产生激波
A supersonic shock wave forms at the sharp tip of the spike,
调整气流 让气流进入进气道
tuning airflow for entry into the inlet chamber.
在发动机短舱外 气流就已经开始进行压缩了
Some compression is already happening here, outside of the nacelle.
在进气道唇部 另一个激波形成
Just at the inlet lip, another shock wave forms,
在进气道内"反射"多次
bounces or "reflects" a few times,
并最终到达进气道的最窄处
and eventually reaches the narrowest part of the inlet passage,
此时超音速的能量终于转换 降低到亚音速状态
where its supersonic energy is finally converted, having slowed to subsonic speeds.
以超音速气流的速度换取压力 密度和温度的增加
The tremendous exchange of energy that happens as supersonic air trades its velocity
是这步巨大能量交换的关键所在
for increased pressure, density and temperature, is key.
虽然喷气发动机内不能直接使用超音速气流
You can't use supersonic air in the jet engine,
但发动机可以像泵一样吸入大量超音速气流 并将其转化为压力
but you can use the jet engine like a pump to take in more and more supersonic air and convert it to pressure.
就像捏花园水管的逆向过程一样 把大量高速水流泵回软管内
It's the garden hose in reverse,
if the fast water stream could be crammed back into the hose.
在进气道最窄的地方有一个开口 以排出一些超音速气流
To that end, there's an opening just before the inlet's narrowest point, to bleed off some supersonic air.
这股气流流过减震器 降低速度 增加压力
It flows through shock traps to slow and pressurize.
围绕发动机为其冷却
It surrounds and cools the engine,
最终重新加入废气气流
and eventually rejoins the exhaust stream,
气流在此重新将压力转换为速度 离开发动机尾部
where it trades pressure for velocity on its way out the back.
这个过程相当重要
This process is so important,
在3.2马赫巡航期间 仅进气锥旁路气流回收的压力
that at Mach 3.2 cruise, just the pressure recovery alone from the inlet spike and bypass air
就能提供惊人的58%的推力
is responsible for an incredible 58% of thrust.
这种妙招之所以可行 还因为8万英尺高空的气压较低
This clever trick is also possible because there's less air pressure at 80,000 feet,
所以不需要在发动机内积攒多大的压力就能释放出高速废气气流
so you don't need to hold or build up as much pressure inside the engine to release a super fast exhaust jet.
在海平面高度附近 空气密度更大
At sea level the air is much thicker.
想象同样的花园水管 但让它水下喷
Imagine that same garden hose, but spraying underwater.
进气锥是可移动的
The spike is adjustable.
进气锥在如此高的速度下想要产生如此大的推力
With this much thrust coming from the inlet spike at such high speeds,
关键在于激波处于正确位置
it's critical that shock waves maintain proper alignment.
在1.6马赫及以上时 进气锥开始持续向后移动
At Mach 1.6 the spike begins to retract and continues moving backwards,
并在达到黑鸟设计巡航速度3.2马赫时 向后移动到最远距离26英寸
to 26 inches of rearward travel at its limit as speed hits Mach 3.2, the Blackbird's designed cruising speed.
进气道喉部的形状随着进气锥的移动而变化
The inlet throat's shape changes as the spike moves.
巡航速度时 进气锥激波刚好位于进气道唇部
At cruise, the spike shock wave sits right at the inlet lip.
再次强调 保持这种预先设计的激波形态至关重要
Again, keeping this pre-designed shock wave pattern is crucial.
例如 某种内部故障导致喷气发动机进气道入口处压力积聚
For example, say some kind of internal error causes pressure build up at the mouth of the jet engine,
推动激波偏离预定位置
pushing shock waves out of alignment.
这一侧的推力就会立即丧失 飞机会突然向一侧偏转
All that thrust is immediately lost, and the plane jerks abruptly to one side,
飞行员的头盔甚至会撞上座舱侧面的窗户
slamming pilots helmets against cockpit windows.
这一过程称为"进气未启动"
This is called an inlet unstart.
进气未启动对SR-71飞行员来说感受很痛苦
Unstarts were harrowing experiences for SR-71 pilots.
飞机会瞬间失去70%的推力
With up to 70% of total thrust disappearing in an instant.
如果检测到进气未启动 机载计算机会立即将进气锥向前伸出并尝试重启
If an unstart is detected, the onboard computer moves the spike forward in an attempt to restart it.
这就是让黑鸟一飞冲天的 大名鼎鼎的J58发动机
So that's it. You've got the famed J58 jet engines for getting the Blackbird off the ground and up to speed,
以及让飞机在超音速稳定巡航的进气锥
and the inlet spikes for comfortable cruise well into the supersonic realm.
整套系统能很好地转换超音速气流的能量
This system is so good at capturing the energy in supersonic airflow
因此 黑鸟飞得越快越省油
that the Blackbird was known to get better fuel mileage the faster it went.
再来了解一下发动机其他几个在系统的关键时刻辅助控制气流的部件
Now, let's examine a few other components at the engine that help keep airflow in check at key points in the system.
计算机控制的前旁通门可排出多余空气 保持进气压力平衡
There are computer controlled forward bypass doors to let off excess air, and keep inlet air pressure balanced.
但这部分慢速气流汇入外部高速气流时会增加阻力
However, this slow air rejoining the outside flow could cause drag.
因此 在发动机前还有一组飞行员可手动控制的旁通门
So, there's another set of bypass doors just before the engine that the pilot can manually control,
可以将空气送入短舱旁通室
which bleed air into the nacelle bypass chamber instead.
在0.5马赫以下 气流可能不足以冷却发动机
Below Mach 0.5 there may not be enough airflow yet for proper cooling.
在短舱中部下方有一个吸气活门 可以打开辅助冷却
There are suck-in doors about halfway down the nacelle that open to help out.
喷气发动机尾部还有一组翼片 用于独立控制加力燃烧室的排气压力
There's a set of flaps at the back of the jet engine to independently control afterburner exhaust pressure,
还有一圈吹入门
and a ring of blow-in doors,
在低于1.2马赫时填充喷口 防止内部出现气流盲区 造成阻力
to help keep the ejector area full at lower speeds and avoid dead spots, which cause drag in the system.
高于2.2马赫时 六条旁通管开启
Above Mach 2.2, there are six bypass tubes,
将喷气发动机压缩机内气体直接送入加力燃烧室
that open to divert air from the jet engine's compressor section directly to the afterburner,
减小发动机内部压力 提高加力燃烧室性能
relieving internal engine pressure and boosting afterburner performance.
超过发动机进气量40%的气流会走这条旁通管 从而显著增加推力
Up to 40% of the engine intake volume can be bypassed in this way, for a significant thrust increase.
进气锥上有一圈小孔
The inlet spike has rows of small holes,
内部有低速时可吸入冷却空气的通道
and interior passages that take in cooling air at low speed.
在高速时 进气锥一圈会有一层薄薄的空气 称为边界层
At higher speeds, a thin layer of air builds up around surfaces, called the boundary layer.
气体附着在表面上流动 边界层会产生一些奇怪的现象
Boundary layers can do weird things as the air sticks to and follows the surface.
在形状弯曲处 边界层可能会分离 阻塞气流 给下游带来不必要的湍流
At curves, air might separate and clog up the flow, causing unwanted turbulence downstream.
而这些小孔可以吸收边界层气流 让进气锥的气流更平顺
These holes bleed off boundary air to keep flow running smoothly.
为了减重 机上没有发动机启动器
For weight reduction, there's no starter on the airplane.
启动发动机需要启动车
Start carts were used,
两台肌肉车发动机并排放置 不带消声器 全速运转
with two muscle-car engines placed side by side, without mufflers, running full blast.
据说机组都很享受启动过程 爽得令人印象深刻
Crew were said to enjoy the start process for its impressive spectacle.
一根带齿轮的轴向上延伸 与喷气发动机底部的变速箱相连
A shaft with gears extends up and connects with a gearbox at the underside of the jet engine,
带动发动机部件旋转起来 开始点火程序
to get everything spinning and start the combustion process.
现在 发动机放一边 来了解下燃油系统
Now let's move away from the engines, for a look at the fuel system.
开场我们已提到 飞机相当多的部分都是油箱
As shown in the intro, fuel tanks make up a large portion of the plane.
33.6吨
起飞时 单台发动机的燃油流量可达每小时74000磅
At takeoff, fuel flow rate could reach 74,000 lbs. per hour for a single engine.
11.4升               40882升
相当于每秒3加仑 每小时10800加仑
That's about 3 gallons of fuel per second, or 10,800 gallons per hour.
11356升
在3.15马赫 燃油效率更高 每小时略低于3000加仑
At Mach 3.15, fuel flow is more efficient, at a little under 3,000 gallons per hour.
油箱与机翼结构融为一体 没有任何额外的气囊或隔档
The tank is incorporated into the wing structure without any additional bladder or barrier.
由于表面镶板设计是可膨胀的
Since panels were designed to expand,
所以缝隙会让燃油在飞机常温时泄露
panel gaps meant fuel would leak from the plane when cold.
维护人员有每小时允许滴油量的图表
Maintenance personnel had charts for allowable drips per hour,
漏油一旦超过某个速度 飞机镶板就必须重新涂抹密封胶
and when that rate was exceeded, the plane's panels had to have sealant reapplied.
由于表面温度过高 为防止自燃 飞机不能使用普通燃油
Surfaces got so hot that normal fuel couldn't be used for risk of auto-ignition from surface heat alone.
人们特意研发名为JP-7的特殊燃油 在466华氏度以下不会自燃
A special fuel called JP-7 was developed which wouldn't spontaneously ignite below 466 degrees Fahrenheit.
三乙基硼通常用于火箭发动机的点火物
要点燃这种燃油 需要一种特殊的化学物质 三乙基硼 简称TEB
To ignite this fuel, a special chemical was required, called triethylborane or TEB for short.
三乙基硼性质相反 遇到空气就会燃烧
TEB, in contrast, ignites on contact with air alone.
先注入一发三乙基硼 让一部分JP-7先燃烧起来
A shot of TEB was injected first to get the JP-7 fuel burning,
带来标志性的绿色启动火焰
which produced the famous green starting flame blast.
燃油中的添加剂可使其用作润滑剂 冷却剂和液压油
Additives in the fuel made it useful as a lubricant, coolant, and hydraulic fluid.
燃油在整个飞机中 尤其是发动机的机械部件中 扮演着上述作用之一
It took on any of these roles throughout the plane, especially in the engine's mechanical components.
SR-71要在起飞后马上空中加油
The SR-71 had to refuel shortly after takeoff
因为满载燃油会对起落架造成压力
because the very heavy full fuel load would stress the plane's landing gear,
且需要过长的跑道升空 等种种限制
and require too much runway for liftoff, among other limitations.
7600米
空中加油通常在25000英尺高度进行
Fueling normally happens at about 25,000 feet,
27216kg
飞机会再加6万磅的燃油
where the plane takes on an additional 60,000 lbs. of fuel.
前起落架舱内有氮气储箱 用于惰化油箱
There are nitrogen containers in the front landing gear compartment to inert fuel tanks –
即氮气泵入油箱 空气排出油箱
meaning air is allowed to vent out as nitrogen is pumped in.
燃油接触不到空气 就可以当成它被惰化了 即化学性质不活泼
With no oxygen near the fuel, it's considered inert, or chemically inactive,
可以极大降低极端压力与温度环境下的爆炸风险
greatly reducing explosion risk in conditions of extreme pressure and heat.
飞行控制面
飞行控制面是飞机机身上影响气流以改变飞机姿态的部件
Flight control surfaces are parts of an airplane's body that influence airflow to change the plane's attitude.
例如 通常一架飞机
For example, a fairly standard airplane
在每个翼尖上都有副翼
has ailerons at each wingtip
两侧副翼运动方向相反 控制飞机滚转
that move opposite one another to roll the plane.
移动尾部的升降舵 控制飞机俯仰
Moving elevators at the tail affects pitch,
移动尾部的方向舵 控制飞机偏航 即绕垂直于飞机的轴旋转
and the rudder controls yaw, or rotation about the airplane's vertical axis.
SR-71有两个巨大的方向舵 置于每台发动机上
The SR-71 has large dual rudders, one above each engine.
三角翼将副翼和升降舵结合成一排襟翼 可同时完成两者工作
The delta wing combines ailerons with elevators into a single row of flaps that handles both tasks.
称为升降副翼
These are called elevons.
左右两侧各为一组
Each side moves as a single unit.
两侧反方向移动 控制飞机滚转
Opposite one another for roll,
两侧同方向移动 控制飞机俯仰
and together for pitch –
或两者混合 用于同时需要一定滚转和俯仰的机动
or some blended combination of both for maneuvers that require some roll and pitch at the same time.
为了实现这种混合的输出控制
To achieve this blended, mixed output,
尾部中央有一套机械装置 叫做混合器
there's a mechanical device in the center tail section called a mixer.
钢缆从驾驶舱内的飞行操纵杆通过滑轮和管道到达混合器
Cables from the flight stick in the cockpit pass through pulleys and tubes to arrive at the mixer.
操纵杆左右控制的钢索在这里控制俯仰
There are separate down and back cable runs for stick side-to-side or roll,
操纵杆上下控制的钢索在这里控制俯仰
and stick front-to-back, or pitch.
在混合器上 俯仰钢索连接到俯仰扇形轮上
At the mixer, pitch cables connect to the pitch quadrant,
扇形轮就是有放置钢索的沟槽的扇形滑轮
which is a partial wheel with channels and attach points.
滚转钢索连接到俯仰扇形轮后方的滚转扇形轮上
Roll cables attach to the roll quadrant behind that.
前方是控制混合输出的双臂曲柄
There's a mixed output bellcrank at the front
上面有推杆 一直连接到各自一侧的升降副翼
with push rods that link to the elevons at either side.
滚转操作会带动整个双臂曲柄左右移动
Roll input moves the entire bellcrank left or right.
因为这会让联动装置左右相反运动
Because linkages are mirrored side to side,
带动两侧升降副翼向相反方向移动
this ends up rotating elevons in opposite directions.
俯仰操作会旋转双臂曲柄自身
Pitch input rotates the bellcrank itself,
带动两侧升降副翼以相同方向移动
which tilts elevons the same way on both sides.
当同时存在俯仰与滚转指令时
When pitch and roll commands happen together,
双臂曲柄会优雅地把指令的混合结果输出给两侧
the bellcrank gracefully blends these commands for a singular output to each side.
这套机械结构太美了 再看一眼吧
This beautiful mechanical device is worth a closer look.
以滚转组件为例
Take the roll components, for example.
有一个力反馈弹簧 让飞行员在操纵杆上感觉到系统中部件的位置
There's a feel spring that compresses to give the pilot felt feedback in the stick
for the position of parts in the system,
因为 稍后我们就会知道 升降副翼本身是由液压驱动的
because, as we'll see in a minute, the elevons themselves are hydraulically controlled.
并没有直接的机械连接
There's no direct mechanical connection.
传动结构往下走 是配平作动器
Moving down the chain, there's a trim actuator.
配平可以为系统带来永久调节功能
Trim adds more permanent adjustment to the system
这样飞行员不必长时间向一个方向带杆
so the pilot doesn't have to hold the stick in one place for long periods of time,
比如在持续侧风环境下
for example to fight a continuous side wind.
系统允许随时调整配平设置
The system still allows moment to moment input on top of the trim setting.
飞行员在驾驶舱控制配平杆
The pilot controls the trim level from the cockpit.
俯仰组件也有这些东西
Pitch components also have these parts.
俯仰的力反馈弹簧在混合器的底部
The pitch feel spring is at the bottom of the mixer.
俯仰配平作动器在后部
The pitch trim actuator is at the back.
仔细观察双臂曲柄如何执行混合输入指令的
Now watch, as the bellcrank executes blended roll and pitch commands,
以及当中的配平设置
with accompanying trim settings.
俯仰系统中还有一个推杆器
Also connected to the pitch system, there's a stick pusher.
自带一个计算机控制的作动器
With its own computer controlled actuator.
推杆器可以抖动操纵杆 在失速时作为警告
The stick pusher can shake the stick as a warning,
还可以为避免失速自动向前推杆
or automatically push the stick forward to avoid or counter a stall.
如果飞机超过一定飞行角度限制 就会发生失速
Stalls can happen, for example, if the plane exceeds certain flight angle limits,
升力突然减小 导致飞机坠落
interrupting lift and causing the plane to fall through the air.
从混合器出来 两侧各种连杆结构将运动传递给几组伺服单元
From the mixer, rods at each side translate movements to individual servo units.
伺服机构将这种物理运动转换为液压 调节每个升降副翼上的传动装置
The servo converts this physical movement into hydraulic pressure to regulate rows of actuators at each elevon.
还有一根传感杆 用来监测升降副翼的位置
It has a sensing rod to monitor elevon position.
内侧的伺服机构再通过一串连杆 把动作传递给外侧伺服机构
From this inboard servo, a train of rods and linkages continues to an outboard servo
从而控制另一组作动器
which controls another set of actuators.
还有单独的一组钢缆 滑轮和液压组件控制每个方向舵
There's a separate set of cables, pulleys, and hydraulic components for each rudder.
方向舵底部的作动器驱动一根直插方向舵中的垂直杆
A rotating post with an attached actuator extends from the rudder stub into the rudder frame.
起落架
飞机前部有一组可转向的前起落架
There's a single steerable nose wheel at the front,
后部有两组主起落架
and twin gear at the back.
奇特的浅灰色轮胎由注入了铝粉的橡胶制成  闪点更高
The peculiar light grey rear tires are made of rubber infused with aluminum powder for a much higher flash point,
即轮胎会被点燃的温度
that is, the temperature at which they could catch fire.
约27个标准气压                               约2-2.4个标准气压
轮胎胎压高达400psi——普通轿车的胎压一般是30-35psi
They're pressurized to an unbelievable 400psi – your average car tire sits at around 30 to 35 psi.
为了防火 内部充的还是不含氧气的氮气 以达到防火的效果
They're also inflated with nitrogen instead of oxygen for fire resistance.
黑鸟的空气动力学特性意味着它着陆速度更高
The Blackbird's aerodynamic qualities mean higher landing speeds overall.
为了进一步减慢飞机速度 减轻起落架的压力
To further slow the plane down and take stress off the wheels,
约280km/h                                   约12.2米
在主轮接地 大约150节空速时 会展开直径为40英尺的减速伞
there's a 40 ft diameter drag chute which is deployed at main gear touchdown, at about 150 knots airspeed.
座舱
现在我们来到机头的位置 了解黑鸟的双座舱
Now, let's head to the front of the plane for a look inside the Blackbird's dual cockpit(s).
飞行员坐在前座舱 负责飞机的驾驶等事务
The pilot sits in the forward cockpit to fly the plane among other duties,
侦察系统官 简称RSO 位于后座舱 负责操纵机载设备
with the Reconnaissance Systems Officer, or RSO, in the rear cockpit to run onboard equipment,
还要引导飞机沿任务路线飞行
and direct navigation along the mission flight path.
来到飞行员座位 来了解下飞机的仪表与操控
Moving to the pilot's position, let's get into the instruments and controls.
前部中央 有一组主飞行仪表
Front and center, there's a grouping of main flight instruments.
姿态仪展示飞机相对地平线的姿态
The attitude indicator shows the plane's position relative to the horizon,
上面紧挨着备份姿态仪
with a backup attitude indicator nearby for redundancy.
下方是水平状态指示器 简称HSI
Below that, the HSI or Horizontal Situation Indicator,
展示飞机航向与 空间中预选方向或预设点 的相对位置
shows the plane's position relative to a heading or preset point in space,
以及飞机与假想方向线之间的关系
and the plane's relationship to the imaginary line from one heading to the next,
可显示剩余距离 侧向偏移量等内容
including remaining distance, side-to-side deviation, and so on.
再下方是一块地图投影仪 使用16mm胶片 内含整个飞行路径
Below that, a map projector, which ran on 16mm film, and contains the entire flight route.
有几块仪表在大多数飞机上也都有
There are a few instruments here which are standard to most airplanes.
高度表 显示高度
The altimeter for altitude,
空速表 显示大致前进速度 单位是节
airspeed for general forward speed in knots,
垂直速度表 显示飞机垂直速度
and vertical air speed for how fast the plane is moving up or down.
在高空 超音速飞行时
At supersonic speeds and very high altitudes,
外部空气条件与飞机外部部件周围的超音速气流都会影响仪表精度
outside air conditions, and supersonic airflow around the plane's exterior components affects instrument accuracy.
因此 SR-71飞行员在巡航时主要依靠三显表
As such, SR-71 pilots relied on the triple display indicator at speed.
第一行是KEAS表 即等效空速表 单位是节
There's the KEAS indicator at the top for knots equivalent airspeed,
它考虑到高空空气的压缩性 会计算出修正后的速度
which takes into account air compressibility at high altitude for an adjusted speed calculation.
作为参考 修正后的速度与传统空速表之间可能存在100节的差异
For reference, there could be up to 100 knots difference
between the normal airspeed indicator and this adjusted reading.
第二行显示高度
Altitude is beneath that,
第三行显示马赫数
and Mach at the bottom.
下方右侧是燃油流量计 单位为千磅每小时
Down and to the right, there are fuel flow gauges measured in thousands of pounds per hour.
旁边是油压表
Oil pressure gauges are nearby.
还有各种系统的液压压力表
There are gauges for hydraulic pressure in various systems.
上方是一组排气相关的仪表 包括排气喷管位置指示器
Above that, a grouping of instruments related to exhaust, including exhaust nozzle position indicators,
与排气温度表
and exhaust temperature.
426.6摄氏度
正常运行温度为800华氏度 可由飞行员手动微调
Normal running temperature is 800 degrees Fahrenheit, and can be manually adjusted or "trimmed" by the pilot.
旁边是火警灯
There are fire warning lights nearby,
转速计 测量发动机转速
and tachometers to measure engine rotation speed.
慢车转速约3900RPM 巡航转速约7100RPM
Idle is about 3900 RPM, while cruise is around 7,100 RPM.
译注: 在加力燃烧室工作时 发动机的转速变化范围很小
发动机转速在飞行全程中变化并不大
That's not much difference in engine rotation speed for all the action happening in that part of the plane.
上面还有个计时器 就是个秒表
There's an elapsed time gauge which is a sort of stopwatch,
原文注:
用得不多 比如监控两点间预期飞行时间
用得不多 但是政府要求装的
Rarely used, but a government requirement.
来到左边 攻角指示器 显示飞机相对飞行方向的夹角
Moving leftward, there's the angle of attack indicator to track the plane's angle relative to its direction of travel.
前文提到 飞机设计巡航时攻角6度
You'll recall from earlier, the plane is designed to sit at about 6 degrees angle of attack at cruise.
下面是一堆与进气道 进气锥 发动机相关的仪表 开关和指示灯
There are gauges, switches, and lights related to the previously shown inlets, spikes, and engines.
在大部分飞行过程中 进气道由机载计算机自动控制
For most of the flight, the inlets are automatically controlled by onboard computers,
不过在需要时 飞行员可手动控制
but the pilot can take manual control if needed.
左右各一个"进气未启动"指示灯
There are left and right inlet unstart warning lights,
左下角是重启开关
with restart switches at the bottom left.
进气锥位置表 里面两根指针 对应两台发动机
There's a spike position gauge, with two indicators, one for each side.
还有进气锥位置控制器
and position switches.
压缩机进气温度表
Compressor inlet temperature,
和压缩机进气压力表 用来检测J58发动机压缩机前的压力情况
and pressure gauges to monitor conditions at the compressor face or front of the J58 jet engine.
21:02 介绍旁通门
这里还有一组开关控制气流旁通门
with a pair of switches for air bypass control in this area.
左侧有推杆/抖杆器开关
There's a stick pusher/shaker switch to the left.
开启时 若飞行员操控飞机接近攻角限制 飞机会抖杆
When turned on, the stick will shake if the pilot is approaching angle of attack limits,
且若飞行员无视抖杆 则飞机会强行向前推杆
and forcefully push the stick forward if the pilot ignores the shaking.
RSO弹射开关用于请求RSO弹射
The RSO bailout switch is used to request bailout,
因为在需要弹射的紧急情况下 后座的RSO需要先走
since the RSO (the backseat officer) should go first in emergency bailout conditions,
以避免打开座舱盖时的种种安全问题
to avoid safety concerns with opening canopies and so on.
RSO弹射指示灯 显示RSO是否已弹射
The RSO ejected light indicates if the RSO has actually ejected.
如果飞行员与RSO之间通讯失灵 这些开关与指示灯也能作为保险
These are also failsafes if the communication system between officers isn't working.
左上角是减速伞放出把手
The drag chute pull handle is up and to the left.
最下面是俯仰 滚转 偏航配平的指示器
At the bottom, there are indicator gauges for pitch, roll, and yaw trim levels.
滚转配平开关在驾驶舱左侧
The roll trim switch is at the left side of the cockpit.
飞行操纵杆上是俯仰与偏航配平开关
A combined pitch and yaw trim switch is located on the flight stick,
左右控制偏航配平 上下控制俯仰配平
with left-to-right for yaw and up-and-down for pitch.
既然说到操纵杆了 就讲讲它上面其他开关吧
While we're at the stick, let's review other controls here.
这个按钮可以让飞行员麦克风在内部与外部通话间切换
There's a button to switch the pilot's microphone between internal or external communication.
右侧的两用按钮 一方面可以激活操纵杆指令
The dual purpose button to the right either activates control stick command
这样飞行员可以在自动驾驶激活时操纵飞机
so the pilot can use the stick during autopilot,
一方面 可以激活飞机在地面时的前轮转向功能
or it can activate nosewheel steering when on the ground.
译注: "除雨系统"并不是雨刮 而是向前风挡喷除雨剂
不可以在前风挡干燥时开启 否则除雨剂会糊在上面 完全遮挡视线
该功能后来被取消
右前方的按钮可以打开除雨系统
A button towards the front turns on the rain removal system.
操纵杆前方还有个多功能扳机
And a multi-purpose trigger at the front
可以控制断开空中加油组件
can control things like disconnecting air refueling components,
中断俯仰或偏航配平等操作
interrupting pitch or yaw trim, and more.
飞行时 两侧方向舵踏板前后移动控制方向舵角度
While in flight, the rudder pedals at each side control rudder angle when pressed inwards from the bottom.
在地面上 方向舵踩下去可以控制各自一侧的刹车
Moving feet up to rotate the pedals controls wheel braking for each side while on the ground.
来到驾驶舱的右侧
Moving now to the right or starboard side of the cockpit,
有燃油管理相关的仪表
there are instruments related to fuel management.
管理好大量燃油的前后平衡 会极大影响飞机的性能
Balancing the massive fuel load front to back greatly affects performance,
因为再次强调 飞机有一定的设计巡航攻角
since the plane, again, is designed to sit at a particular angle.
主油量表 单位磅
There's the main fuel level gauge in pounds.
下方 重心指示
Beneath that, the center of gravity indicator.
燃油系统会从前部油箱往后供油
The fuel system draws from forward tanks and works backwards,
所以随着燃油的消耗 飞机的重心会后移
so the center of gravity will move aft as fuel is consumed.
在巡航时 飞机的重心会后移25%
At speed, this center of gravity has shifted 25% towards the back.
有一个燃油前向转移开关 开启时燃油会向前配平
There's a fuel forward transfer switch that moves fuel back into forward tanks when switched on.
还有一个对应的燃油后向转移开关 必须按住才能让燃油向后配平
And a corresponding fuel aft transfer switch, which moves fuel rearward, and must be held down to operate.
下方有个油箱压力表
There's a fuel tank pressure gauge at the bottom,
还有测量几个氮气瓶的仪表
and gauges to measure nitrogen quantity in various tanks,
26:21 介绍氮气用处
氮气用来惰化油箱 我们在燃油系统中解释过
which is used for inerting, as we saw in the fuel system explanation.
一个放油开关可以快速排掉数千磅的燃油
There's a fuel dump switch to quickly dump thousands of pounds of fuel,
用于诸如需要快速减轻重量的紧急情况
for example to drop weight in an emergency situation.
旁边是紧急燃油切断开关
Emergency fuel shutoff switches are nearby.
然后我们来到驾驶舱左侧
Now let's head over to the left or port side of the cockpit.
有几个旋钮控制驾驶舱空调 负责温度 面部加温 飞行服加温
There's a grouping of dials for environmental controls, such as cockpit temperature, face heat and suit heat,
即为飞行员头盔与飞行服加温
which control heating in the pilot's helmet and suit,
原文注: 为保护机载设备 驾驶舱温度不可超过140华氏度(60摄氏度)
机组两人应该也同意这样的设定
旁边还有个带开关的温度表 可以切换显示哪个系统的温度
and a nearby temperature gauge with a switch to select which system it should display.
下方是座舱高度表
Near the bottom there's a cabin altitude gauge.
3048-7924.8m
机组可以调节座舱高度范围 10000英尺-26000英尺
Crew could choose cabin pressurization equivalent to 10,000 or 26,000 ft.
下方是液氧含量指示表
And a liquid oxygen level indicator beneath.
液氧转化为气态 泵入机组的头盔中供他们呼吸
Liquid oxygen is converted to gas and pumped into crew's helmets for breathing.
旁边是起落架手柄 与对应的指示灯 开关等
The landing gear lever is nearby, with associated indicator lights, switches, and so on.
座舱左侧壁 是两个油门杆
As we pivot all the way to the left side wall, we see the dual throttle levers.
上面有个按钮切换飞行员麦克风
There's a button here to toggle the pilot's microphone.
下方有个开关 用于手动激活进气锥重启程序
And a switch beneath that to manually initiate the inlet spike restart sequence.
25:00 介绍TEB的用处
每个油门杆下方都有TEB计数器 统计已经用掉了几发TEB
Each throttle channel has a TEB counter to track how many shots of TEB are used,
每侧共有16发TEB可供使用
from a starting total of 16 shots per side.
举例来说 油门杆前推到限制位 对应通常发动机推力
For example, the throttles move forward up to a limit which corresponds to normal engine power.
飞行员需将油门抬起过限位装置才能启动加力燃烧室
The pilot must lift throttles up over this detent to engage afterburners.
此时会打一发TEB来启动加力燃烧室
Doing so fires a shot of TEB to start the afterburners,
每次这样操作 计数器会减一
and the counters tick down each time this happens.
加力燃烧室的推力在油门杆行程内是可调节的
Afterburner power is controllable from min to max along the stick travel.
油门后方是氧气设定控制面板
There's an oxygen settings control panel behind that.
旁边一个手柄可以放出座舱盖
A nearby pull handle will jettison the canopy.
这里还有无线电面板
Other panels here include a radio panel,
备用氧气面板
standby oxygen panel,
灯光面板 比如控制着陆灯等
a panel for various lights such as landing gear lights and more.
前面是调整地图投影的面板
Controls for the map projector are found towards the front of this panel area.
来到右侧的控制面板
Corresponding banks of controls on the starboard side
这里控制诸如内部通信系统
handle things like internal comms system,
辅助飞行 着陆 起飞 自动驾驶等的计算机导航系统
computer navigation aids for flying, landing and takeoff, autopilot, and more.
后座上也有很多相同的仪表 开关与指示器 还有些其他重要仪表
The rear cockpit echoes many of the same gauges, switches, and indicators, with some crucial additions.
有一个视景监视器可以让RSO直接看到飞机下方的情况
There's a view sight monitor which lets the RSO see directly beneath the plane,
并可设置放大倍数等
with magnification settings, and more.
下方是雷达显示屏
A radar display sits beneath that,
和一个大型地图投影仪
and a large map projector pane.
51:40 介绍天文惯性导航系统
右侧控制面板负责天文惯性导航设备 我们稍后会提到
There's a control panel for the Astro Inertial Navigation device, which we'll cover in a bit.
还有控制侦查设备与指示灯的面板
There's a panel with controls and indicators for reconnaissance equipment.
左侧的控制装置包括用于启动机载防御系统的DEF面板
Controls at the left side include a DEF panel to engage onboard defensive systems,
可以抵御地对空 空对空导弹 企图拦截的敌方战机等各种威胁
which could counter any threats to the plane, from things like surface to air missiles, air to air missiles,
hostile fighter intercept attempts, and so on.
后座也有无线电与内部通信控制系统
There are also radio and intercom controls in this area.
镜头拉远 我们还能看到座舱内的其他东西
As we move away from the controls, we can take in other items in these cockpits.
RSO的座位有可收放的遮阳板
The RSO has retractable sun shades.
而飞行员座位有一个可调节的遮阳板
The pilot has a positionable sun visor with wings.
如果不加遮挡 高空的强光会使飞行员几乎无法看清仪表
Sun glare at altitude could make instrument visibility almost impossible if not blocked.
两个座舱都有小镜子 能让他们看到自己
Both cockpits have small mirrors to help crew see themselves,
因为机组穿着笨重飞行服在狭小空间内行动不便
due to the difficulty of some actions in their bulky flight suits in confined quarters.
飞行员座位有一个可伸缩的潜望镜
The pilot has a retractable periscope
可以观察飞机机尾的情况 如发动机起火 尾迹 放油 检查方向舵位置
to view the plane looking aft for things like engine fires, contrailing, fuel dumping, and to check rudder position.
窗户的内外玻璃层之间有空气间隙
Windows have inner and outer panes with an air gap.
外层玻璃在巡航时温度可达400-500华氏度
Glass at the outside reached temperatures of 400-500 degrees Fahrenheit at cruise,
内层玻璃的温度在250华氏度左右
with the interior pane's surface in the 250 degree (121 C) range.
-40摄氏度
座舱需要泵入-40华氏度的空气
The cockpit had to have air pumped in at -40 degrees,
15.6摄氏度
才能把内部控制在舒适的60华氏度 让穿着飞行服的机组感到舒适
to keep interior temps at a comfortable 60 degrees for crew, who wore their own climate controlled flight suits.
飞行服具有多个关键的分层
The suits themselves have various critical layers,
首先贴身的薄尼龙舒适层
starting with a thin nylon comfort layer against the skin,
其次是充气橡胶囊层 可在紧急弹射的情况下
followed by an inflatable rubber bladder layer for added warmth against cold air or water
提高保暖性 抵御冷空气或水的侵袭
in the event of emergency exit from the cockpit.
鱼网层可帮助飞行服在充气时保持适当的形状
A fishnet type layer helps the suit keep its proper shape when inflated,
标志性的橙色外层可抵御800华氏度的高温
and the iconic orange outer layer which is fire resistant up to 800 F.
手套和头盔固定点有金属环
There are metal rings for glove and helmet attach points.
还有呼吸管与微气候调节管
There are connections for climate and breathing air.
小腿有便于取放物品的拉链口袋
There are easily accessible leg zipper pockets,
大腿上有魔术贴 可放置重要文件
and velcro pads just above knees for sticking important documents.
头盔面窗带遮阳板
The helmet has a face shield with a sun visor,
和用于挤出食物进食的管子
and a feeding port for squeezing food out of tubes.
面部周围有氯丁橡胶密封圈 内部为海平面压力 以便舒适呼吸
There's a neoprene seal around the face to allow pressurization to sea level for comfortable breathing,
而飞行服的其他部分则与驾驶舱的压力水平相匹配
where the rest of the suit matched cockpit pressure levels.
座椅头枕处有降落伞
The seat has a parachute in the head rest,
固定在支撑架上 弹射时可在支撑架上滑动
and is anchored to a support rack upon which it slides during the ejection process.
底部有线缆连接到飞行鞋后跟的金属支架上
There are cables at the bottom for attachment to metal brackets at the heel of each boot.
弹射时 线缆会将飞行员的脚拉紧靠在座椅框架上
These cables pull the pilot's feet tight to the seat frame during ejection
防止弹射时四肢撞到座舱
to avoid striking limbs as the seat blasts out of the cockpit.
侦查设备
机头和侧舱内装有用于实现侦查功能和特定任务目标的组件
The nose and side bays at the front of the plane
have components for both airplane functionality and mission-specific objectives.
我将展示放大后的各个组件
I'll show you the zoomed in individual units,
然后给大家看看它们从8万英尺高空侦查地球表面的范围和能力
and then we'll zoom out so you can see their range and capabilities from 80,000 ft down to the earth's surface.
空速管柱是一根装有各种探头的细管
The pitot mast is a thin tube with various probes
用于向机载计算机和仪器提供空气压力数据 如空速 攻角等
which feeds air pressure data to onboard computers and instruments for things like airspeed, angle of attack, and more.
整个机头可以拆卸 在不同的飞行中可以根据任务目标进行更换
The entire nose is interchangeable and can be swapped out between flights to suit mission objectives.
共有三种机头 其中两种配有不同类型的雷达
There are three noses, two with different radar types,
一种带有光学条形相机 如画面所示
and an optical bar camera which I've featured here.
光学条形相机可携带10500英尺长 5英寸宽的胶片卷轴
The optical bar camera had film reels that carried 10,500 ft of 5-inch wide film.
相比之下 一部90分钟的电影需要使用8100英尺的35毫米胶片
For comparison, a normal 90 minute movie would use 8,100 feet of 35mm film.
它还可以拍摄立体影像 更易地识别目标
It could also film in stereo vision to help identify objectives easier.
往后 有液氧供应瓶
Moving aft, there are liquid oxygen supply bottles.
还有装有SR-71防御系统组件的舱段
There are bays which house components for the SR-71's defensive systems.
再往后 还有一个装有雷达记录设备的舱段
Further aft, there's a bay with radar recording equipment.
黑鸟不寻常的飞行速度和高度
The Blackbird's unusual speed and altitude
往往会激活飞行路径上的敌方雷达和导弹系统
tended to activate hostile radar and missile systems along its flight path.
飞机可以捕捉并分析这些信号 以便更好了解它们的能力
These signals could be captured and analyzed to better understand their capabilities.
后面的舱段装有技术目标相机 可以对较小特定区域进行更详细的拍摄
The bays behind that hold technical objective cameras for more detailed photography of smaller, specific areas.
后座的后方是天文惯性导航系统
Just behind the rear cockpit, there's the Astro Inertial Navigation System (ANS)
用于精确监控飞机位置
to precisely monitor airplane location.
它可以在飞机离开机库后30秒内跟踪三组恒星 白天晚上都能用
It would track three star groups within 30 seconds after leaving the hangar, no matter the time of day.
在全球任何地方以超音速飞行 SR-71都能把位置精确到300英尺内
The SR-71's location could be pinpointed to within 300 feet anywhere in the world, even at Mach speeds.
当时离全球定位系统卫星的出现还有很久
This was well before the existence of GPS satellites.
此外 在这些舱段和隔间中还有电池 无线电设备 天线和计算机
Also in these bays and compartments there are batteries, radio equipment, antennas, and computers
用于支持或辅助与任务目标 飞机等相关的其他组件
that run or assist other components related to mission goals, airplane function, and more.
画面中是离远看 每个组件看到的视野范围
And here's a zoomed out diagram to show you what each component sees.
蓝色区域 光学条形摄像机可以连续拍摄82英里长 2.3英里宽的区域
The optical bar camera can continuously photograph an 82 mile wide by 2.3 miles long patch.
橙色区域 雷达可以监控距离飞行路径23到115英里的11英里见方区域
Radar can monitor an 11 mile area from 23 to 115 miles from the flight path.
绿色区域 (雷达等)信号记录仪最远可以看到地平线
Signal (radar etc.) recorders can see from horizon to horizon.
黄色区域 技术目标相机可以锁定并拍摄16英里见方内数百个目标
Technical objective cameras locate and photograph hundreds of targets to within 6 inches of resolution
分辨率小于6英寸
within a 16 mile range side to side.
也许SR-71的特别之处在于它的罕见
Perhaps what makes the SR-71 so special is its rarity.
让合适的人才聚集在一起 有适当的资金 让他们充分施展才华
To have the right people and talents come together, with proper funding,
and be allowed to flex their talents fully,
真的是一件非常难得的事情
is apparently a very rare thing indeed,
往往会创造很多经久不衰的传奇故事
and often results in legends that persist.
大家好 我是Animagraffs的创作者Jake
Hey everyone, Jake here, creator of Animagraffs.
感谢大家来我的频道欣赏我的作品
First of all thanks for being on the channel and enjoying my work!
这项目做起来可太爽了
This project was AWESOME to create
av1551859360
我之后会发布一期幕后花絮视频
and I'm going to be releasing a behind the scenes video shortly after the release of this one,
详细介绍本期视频背后的各种细节
detailing everything that went into making this project.
从我深入挖掘的研究过程
From the research that I had to find and dig deep to get,
到建模
to crafting the model,
到制作组件 渲染 绑定骨骼 让这些机械部件能动起来
and doing the materials, and rendering, and the rigs -- so, building the moving mechanical objects.
项目中的许多部件在现实生活中就是这样工作的!
The items in these projects, many of them actually work how they would in real life!
这些都是真实还原
These are real recreations,
我想带大家进入制作Animagraffs一期视频背后的神奇和疯狂之中
and I want to show you how I do it and bring you into the magic and the madness of making Animagraffs.
会很轻松愉快 我还会讲几个笑话 值得期待
I'll be entertaining and I might even tell a few light jokes here and there so something to look forward to.
那么 之后见啦!
Anyway, Later!